A Guide to the Jean Packard Papers on Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 1965-2010
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Jean Packard Papers on Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 1965-2010
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 06-77
1.0 linear feet
The Jean Packard Papers on Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations consist of 1.0 linear feet, span the years 1965-2010, and contains material related to the operations of the organization such as award dinner programs, award nomination submissions, correspondence, newsletters, legislative priorities, and governance documents.
Packard, Jean R. (1923-2014)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Items donated through the efforts of Merrily Pierce in 2013
Historical and Biographical Information
The Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations is a county-wide citizens’ activity umbrella organization active since 1940. Its members are civic associations and homeowner associations who pay annual dues. It is non-partisan, volunteer, and non-profit. The federation has a board of directors made up of the following: its nine officers; its committee leadership (budget and finance; citizen association services; human services; education; environment; land use; legislation; resolutions; and transportation), and its district leadership (representatives and council chairmen from the following eight districts: Braddock; Hunter Mill; Lee: Mason: Mount Vernon; Providence; Springfield; and Sully). The Federation sets legislative priorities, such as tree preservation and open space conservation, and comments at public hearings, through written statements, in task forces and commissions, and through the media. It hosts public policy and public affairs programs in addition to monthly general membership programs, a Public Safety Town Meeting, and multi-faceted all-day Saturday programs. Federation members liaise with and represent the Federation with other organizations in Fairfax County such as the Airports Advisory Committee and the Citizen Corps Council.
Jean R. Packard was born in Ohio on April 15, 1923. After the outbreak of World War II, she joined the Women’s Army Corps. She earned a journalism degree from the University of Montana, Missoula in 1948 and edited three weekly newspapers in Southwestern Ohio from 1955 to 1957. From 1958 to 1970, she worked for the National School of Forestry and Conservation and wrote editorials for the International Union for the Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources from 1965 to 1972.
Packard’s first leadership role in Fairfax County was as president of the Lee Forest Civic Association in the 1950s. She became active in the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations in 1962 and served as its president, first and second vice president, corresponding secretary, and bulletin editor. The Federation honored Packard as Fairfax County Citizen of the Year for 1985 at its 36th annual award dinner. In subsequent years, Packard served as the Federation’s awards committee chairperson.
Packard was involved in the Federation in addition to being a long-time public servant and advocate for environmental issues. Elected in 1972 to the Fairfax County Board of Supervisors, she held the position as chairwoman until 1975. She later served on the boards of the Northern Virginia Regional Park Authority and Soil and Water Conservation Board, the latter as an appointee of Governor Mark Warner. She was chair of the Northern Virginia Conservation Trust (the organization renamed its life-time achievement award in her honor). She was a national board member of the Sierra Club.
Packard fought rapid development in Fairfax County by working to protect water supplies and slow down the expansion of sewer service until treatment plants could handle the increased volume. She helped to downzone and protect the Occoquan watershed. Her critics accused her of blocking all growth; she countered that she favored “controlled growth,” as opposed to no growth.
The Jean R. Packard Occoquan Center in Occoquan Regional Park is named in honor of her and The Fred Packard Center in Annandale, Virginia is named after Jean’s husband. Fred Packard served as a director of both the Fairfax County Park Authority and the Northern Virginia Regional Park Authority. Jean Packard died at age 91 on October 21, 2014.
Scope and Content
Series 1: Administration, 1995-2001, Box 1
This series contains material relating to the administration of the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations including legislative priorities and governance documents.
Series 2: Correspondence, 1983-2003, Box 1
This series contains correspondence from the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations (the Federation), sent between 1983 and 2003. These include memos, letters, and email from the Federation about policy positions on subjects such as the transfer of National and Washington Dulles airports to local authority (as the airports were called in 1985), changes for I-66 car pool requirements, and campaign finance; invitations to speak at events sponsored by the Federation; and event logistics for candidate debates and annual dinners, among other public programs hosted by the Federation. Some of the more prominent recipients of correspondence from the Federation included Senator Paul S. Trible, Jr. (multiple in 1985, 1987), Senator John W. Warner (multiple in 1985, 1987, 1996), Congressman Frank R. Wolf (multiple in 1985, 1988), Congressman Stanford R. Parris (multiple in 1985, 1988), Congressman Tom Davis (in 2001), Virginia Governor Mark Warner (multiple in 1996 and 2002), Virginia Governor James Gilmore III (in 1999), Virginia Governor L. Douglas Wilder (in 1992), Virginia Governor Gerald Baliles (in 1989), Lieutenant Governor Timothy M. Kaine (in 2002), Washington Post publisher Donald E. Graham (in 1985), Chairman of the Federal Communications Commissioner Reed Hundt (in 1994), and a plethora of Fairfax County officials and Virginia state senators and delegates. The correspondence was sent in the name of the Federation president or corresponding secretary. In some cases, there are responses back to the Federation, such as 1989 letters from Senator John W. Warner, from Virginia State Senator Joseph V. Gartlan, Jr., and from Virginia Delegate Dorothy S. McDiarmid in response to memos initially sent by the Federation.
Series 3: Bulletins, 1965-1994, Box 1
This series contains newsletters published by the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations.
Series 4: Fairfax County Citizen of the Year, 1969-2010, Box 2
This series contains materials relating to the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations’ annual awards dinner celebrating the Fairfax County Citizen of the Year. The name of the award presented to the honoree changed over the years from The Washington Star Citizenship Trophy to The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy to The Washington Post Citizenship Cup as well as The Washington Post Citizen of the Year. Starting at the 25th Annual Awards Dinner in 1975, Citations of Merit for Citizen Service were also bestowed. This series contains programs from the awards dinners and nomination submission forms.
Arrangement
Series 1: Administration, 1995-2001, Box 1
Series 2: Correspondence, 1983-2003, Box 1
Series 3: Bulletins, 1965-1994, Box 1
Series 4: Fairfax County Citizen of the Year, 1969-2010, Box 2
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bio - Packard, Jean; Jean Packard Oral History file in Braddock’s True Gold Collection - MSS 13-02; Northern Virginia Conservation Council Papers - MSS 05-58
None
Index Terms
Citations of Merit for Citizen Service; Fairfax Citizen of the Year; Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations; Packard, Jean (1923-2014); The Washington Post Citizen of the Year; The Washington Post Citizenship Cup; The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy; The Washington Star Citizenship Trophy
Container List
- Series 1: Administration, 1995-2001
  - Restated Articles of Incorporation, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Legislative Issues, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Index of Papers of the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1983-2003
  - Correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1986-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1998-2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series 3: Bulletins, 1965-1994
  - Bulletin of the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, Volume 12, Number 9, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bulletin of the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, selected monthly issues for 1989 (February, April, May, June, September, October), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bulletin of the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, Volume 38, Numbers 4, 6, 7; Volume 39, Numbers 1, 3, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bulletin of the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, Volume 40, Numbers 1-9, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bulletin of the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, Volume 41, Numbers 1, 2, 4, 5, 6, 10, 12, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bulletin of the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, Volume 42, Numbers 1-8, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bulletin of the Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, Volume 43, Numbers 1-10, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series 4: Fairfax County Citizen of the Year, 1969-2010
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 19th Annual Awards Dinner and Washington Star Citizenship Trophy Presentation to Harriet Hunt, 1969 February 27 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 21st Annual Awards Dinner and Washington Star Citizenship Trophy Presentation to Elizabeth S. Hartwell, 1971 March 23 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 22nd Annual Awards Dinner and Washington Star Citizenship Trophy Presentation to Louise Palmer, 1972 March 21 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 23rd Annual Awards Dinner and Washington Star Citizenship Trophy Presentation to Carl L. Zimmer, 1973 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 24th Annual Awards Dinner and Washington Star Citizenship Trophy Presentation to Lt. Col. Pauline Houston and Lt. Col. William Houston, 1974 May 3 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 25th Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Star Citizenship Trophy Presentation to J. Sidney Holland, 1975 May 9 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 30th Annual Awards Dinner and Washington Star Citizenship Trophy Presentation to James M. Goins, 1980 May 23 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 31st Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Star Citizenship Trophy Presentation to John E. Lynch, 1981 May 29 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 32nd Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy Presentation to Carrington Williams, 1982 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 33rd Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy Presentation to Mary Grace Lintz, 1983 May 3 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 34th Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy Presentation to Eleanor Kennedy, 1984 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 35th Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy Presentation to Toni Winters McMahon, 1985 May 9 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 36th Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy Presentation to Jean R. Packard, 1986 May 7 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 37th Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy Presentation to James M. Rees, 1987 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 38th Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy Presentation to Barbara Shanahan, 1988 May 16 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 39th Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy Presentation to Philip M. Reilly, 1989 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 40th Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy Presentation to John Knox Singleton, 1990 May 18 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 41st Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy Presentation to James Scott, 1991 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 42nd Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy Presentation to George L. Barker, 1992 May 29 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 43rd Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Trophy Presentation to Kathryn A. MacLane, 1993 April 23 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations & The Washington Post, 44th Annual Awards Dinner and 1993 Citizen of the Year - Dr. Richard J. Ernst, 1994 April 9 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 45th Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Cup Presentation to Martha K. Glennan, 1995 May 13 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 46th Annual Awards Dinner and Washington Post Citizenship Cup Presentation to Edward H. Bersoff, 1996 March 16 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 48th Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizenship Cup Presentation to Minerva Wilson Andrews, 1998 Match 27 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 49th Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizen of the Year 1998 - Gerald T. Halpin, 1999 April 11 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 50th Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post Citizen of the Year 1999 - Robert G. Hunt, 2000 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 51st Annual Awards Dinner and The Washington Post 2000 Citizen of the Year - Glenn and Betty Stroup, 2001 March 30 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 52nd Annual Awards Dinner and the Washington Post 2001 Citizen of the Year - Frank de la Fe, 2002 April 12 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations, 53rd Annual Awards Dinner and the Washington Post 2002 Citizen of the Year - Mary Anne Lecos, 2003 April 6 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations & The Washington Post, 54th Annual Awards Banquet - Joseph L. Ritchey, 2004 April 25 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations & The Washington Post, 56th Annual Awards Banquet - Marlene Blum, 2006 March 19 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations & The Washington Post, 57th Annual Awards Banquet - Sally B. Ormsby, 2007 March 11 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Fairfax County Federation of Citizens Associations & The Washington Post, 60th Annual Awards Banquet - M.L. Clark Tyler, 2010 May 2 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Fairfax County Citizen of the Year Nomination Submissions for 1996, 1981-1997 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Fairfax County Citizen of the Year Nomination Submissions for 1999, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Fairfax County Citizen of the Year Nomination Submissions for 2000, 1988-2001 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Fairfax County Citizen of the Year Nomination Submissions for 2002, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 37)